Guide to the Joseph Starke Sims papers, 1819-1903 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph Starke Sims papers 1819-1903 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sims, Joseph Starke.
2.4 linear feet Extent: 295 Items
RL.01206
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Joseph Starke Sims papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1978-1991. This collection forms part of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection, 1695-1955 and undated.
Biographical Note
Joseph Starke Sims was a Civil War Confederate officer, cotton grower, and South Carolina senator.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, financial records, legal documents, clippings, account books, commissions, addresses and speeches, and a diploma. Correspondence concerns chiefly cotton growing, trade and prices; slaves who worked in cotton fields; financial matters; Washington, D.C. politics, with references to Henry Clay and John Calhoun; state and national politics; descriptions of newly settled areas of Mississippi and California; and a cholera outbreak in Charleston (1832). Civil War letters detail problems at Fort Sumter (1861), and often refer to economic difficulties and shortages in South Carolina. Other Civil War letters are also written from Manassas, Alabama, and Mississippi. One letter from Mississippi details the desperation of women left alone and unable to flee before the advancing Union Army. Post-war letters reveal the problems of Reconstruction in South Carolina. Many of the letters are to Sims' wife Jane Emily Sims (Farnandis).
Includes an autobiographical letter from J. K. Paulding, author and statesman, and an essay by the same, entitled "The history of Uncle Sam and his boys." Some of Sims' addresses and one of the legal documents concern Nullification, which Sims' strongly supported. Other documents include an obituary for Franklin H. Elmore, plantation and general account books, and some material on Sims' student days at South Carolina College (ca. 1817-1819), which includes a letter to his brother in 1819 "in defence of General Jackson," and his "treatment of the Indians."
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Paulding, James Kirke, 1778-1860; Elmore, F. H. (Franklin Harper), 1799-1850; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Sims, Jane Emily; South Carolina College -- Alumni and alumnae; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 9th; Confederate States of America -- Officers -- Correspondence; Plantations -- Records -- South Carolina; Cotton growing -- South Carolina; Slavery -- South Carolina; Legislators -- South Carolina -- Correspondence; Cholera -- South Carolina -- Charleston; Nullifcation (States' rights); Secession; Fort Sumter (Charleston, S.C.)--Siege, 1861; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Charleston (S.C.)--Social life and customs; Mississippi -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; California -- Description and travel; Account books
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1823-1895 (Box 1)
  - Legal Papers, 1824-1867 (Box 2)
  - Financial Papers, 1838-1888
  - Addresses and Writings, 1824-1903
  - Miscellany, 1819-1891
  - Volumes, 1819-1871
  - Legal Papers and Correspondence, 1800s (Box 3)
  - Plantation Account Book, 1854
  - Facsimile of Plantation Account Book